Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 65: Miracles of Mary, circa 1720; Manuscript on parchment, mostly in gatherings of 10 leaves. The main body of the text is written in 2 columns of 15 lines, in black with the usual rubrics (opening lines of individual texts, the name of Mary, the original owner's 
  - MIRACLE 17, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 50v-52v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the poor widow, the marriage of whose daughters was arranged by the Virgin.
  - PAINTING 29, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 52v. (Unitid 65)
    The widow stands before the Virgin's image whilst her daughters are shown seated in the background. The text in the top margin reads 'How she relieved the old woman of her wretchedness'.
  - PAINTING 30, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 53r. (Unitid 65)
    The widow is buried whilst her daughters look on.
  - MIRACLE 18, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 53v-55r. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the two brother scribes, one of whom had been writing a copy of the Miracles of Mary and whose soul was rescued by the Virgin.
  - PAINTING 31, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 55r. (Unitid 65)
    The two scribes, described in the text as 'the two brothers'.
  - PAINTING 32, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 55v. (Unitid 65)
    The Virgin rescues the scribe's soul from devils.
  - MIRACLE 19, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 56r-57r. (Unitid 65)
    The story of St. George the Younger whom the Virgin rescued from prison.
  - PAINTING 33, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 57v. (Unitid 65)
    St. George in prison on his iron griddle; the Virgin appears to him in the form here of a green dove. The text reads 'How she appeared to him'.
  - MIRACLE 20, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 58r-59v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the old priest called Kät'ir, whom the Virgin defended when he was banished from his church.
  - PAINTING 34, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 59v. (Unitid 65)
    [half-page] The Virgin addresses the guardian of the church.
  - PAINTING 35, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 60r. (Unitid 65)
    The Virgin blesses the old priest, whilst in the top left-hand corner the church guardian is shown expelling him.
  - blank, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 60v. (Unitid 65)
  - MIRACLE 21, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 61r-63r. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the dyer called Näzib who was rescued at the Virgin's behest by St. George from prison where he was falsely detained.
  - PAINTING 36, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 63v. (Unitid 65)
    On the left, Näzib and his brother receive the pieces of cloth for dying; top-right, St. George attacks the judge who condemned Näzib falsely; bottom-right, he is shown in prison.
  - PAINTING 37, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 64r. (Unitid 65)
    Näzib is acquitted and receives his pardon from the qadi.
  - MIRACLE 22, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 64v-66v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the man with a club foot who was healed by the Virgin.
  - PAINTING 38, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 67r. (Unitid 65)
    On the left, the man tells the bishop of his ailment, whilst on the right, he is cured of his club foot and gives thanks to the image of the Virgin. The text reads 'she cured the Frank ['afrengawi].
  - PAINTING 39, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 67v. (Unitid 65)
    The man shows the bishop his healed foot.
  - MIRACLE 23, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 68r-69r. (Unitid 65)
    The story of Bishop Mercurius whom the Virgin cured of leprosy.
  - PAINTING 40, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 69v. (Unitid 65)
    Top, the archbishop tells Mercurius he cannot serve as a priest whilst he has leprosy; bottom, Mercurius takes his leave of his congregation (?). The text at the top of the painting simply names Mercurius, who seems to be shown twice with his robe pulled off his shoulders to expose his leprosy.
  - PAINTING 41, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 70r. (Unitid 65)
    On the right, Mercurius stands before the Virgin, who heals him, whilst on the left, he shows the archbishop that he is now cured.
  - MIRACLE 24, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 70v-72r. (Unitid 65)
    the story of the woman of Haarlem (Hartälrom in the text here) with a lame foot who was healed by the Virgin Mary.
  - PAINTING 42, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 72v. (Unitid 65)
    The woman is born on a litter by her relatives and placed before the image of the Virgin. The text reads 'the lame woman'.
  - PAINTING 43, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 73r. (Unitid 65)
    The Virgin cures the woman, who is then shown standing before the Virgin's image.
  - MIRACLE 25, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 73v-77v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of Abbess Sophia who conceived a child, and whose reputation was saved by the Virgin.
  - PAINTING 44, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 78r. (Unitid 65)
    The Virgin supervises the delivery of Sophia's child by angels, who then hand the child to Felix [Filkes in the text here].
  - PAINTING 45, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 78v. (Unitid 65)
    the bishop addresses the nuns
  - PAINTING 46, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 79r. (Unitid 65)
    Sophia tells her story to the bishop, and Felix [Filkes] verifies it, producing the child.
  - MIRACLE 26, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 79v-81r. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the rich and dissolute man, Barok of Finqi, who was saved by the Virgin Mary because of his devotion to her.
  - PAINTING 47, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 81v. (Unitid 65)
    Barok gives a banquet.
  - PAINTING 48, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 82r. (Unitid 65)
    A composite picture showing variously Barok being attacked by his enemies; Barok being nursed; Barok telling his sins to the priest; and the Virgin Mary who oversees all these events.
  - MIRACLE 27, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 82v-84r. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the deacon Anastasius.
  - PAINTING 49, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 84v. (Unitid 65)
    Anastasius stands before the Virgin's image, and (right) she appears to him in a dream in which she tells him he will join her in Paradise. The text simply identifies Anastasius [Anest'asyos].
  - MIRACLE 28, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 85r-88v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the monk of the monastery of Abba Samu'el in Qälmon.
  - blank, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 89r. (Unitid 65)
  - PAINTING 50, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 89v. (Unitid 65)
    The man is attacked by his fellow monks and seized by them. The text reads 'how they seized him'.
  - PAINTING 51, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 90r. (Unitid 65)
    The monk stands in prayer before the Virgin's image, having now lost his cap with which he miraculously made a breach in the wall to escape. The text reads 'how threw off the cap from his head'.
  - MIRACLE 29 [numbered as 30], circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 90v-92v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the cannibal of Qemer whose soul was saved by the Virgin Mary.
  - PAINTING 52, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 92v. (Unitid 65)
    A composite picture showing the cannibal dismembering his relatives; giving water to a leper; the farmers who set out to catch him. the two brief texts simply identify 'the cannibal' and 'the farmers'.
  - PAINTING 53, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 93r. (Unitid 65)
    A composite picture showing Christ commanding the devil to surrender the cannibal's soul; St. Michael weighing the cannibal's soul in the balance; the Virgin Mary with Christ's blessing retrieving the cannibal's soul.
  - MIRACLE 30 [numbered as 31], circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 93v-94v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the widow's son who was a thief, whom the Virgin saved at his mother's request.
  - PAINTING 54, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 94v. (Unitid 65)
    The thief steals from the Virgin's church.
  - PAINTING 55, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 95r. (Unitid 65)
    Top, the thief's mother prays before the Virgin's image; bottom, the thief is rescued by St. Michael from his bonds.
  - MIRACLE 31 [numbered as 32], circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 95v-96v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the woman who gave birth in a storm at sea with the Virgin's protection.
  - PAINTING 56, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 96v. (Unitid 65)
    [three-quarter page] The Virgin shields the woman and her child with her cloak, while the congregation look on from the shore. The text reads 'How she saved her'.
  - PAINTING 57, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 97r. (Unitid 65)
    The woman and her child amongst the congregation of her church. The text simply reads 'the faithful'.
  - MIRACLE 32 [numbered as 33], circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 97v-98v. (Unitid 65)
    The story of the Virgin and the thirsty dog.
  - PAINTING 58, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 99r. (Unitid 65)
    The Virgin gives water to the dog from her slipper, whilst below, her companions attempt to drive the dog away from the water jars.
  - blank, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 99v. (Unitid 65)
  - PAINTING 59, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 100r. (Unitid 65)
    The Virgin and Child with the archangels and below, the prostrate figure of the donor or commissioner of the manuscript.
  - blank, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 100v. (Unitid 65)
  - blank except for two lines of pen trials, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 101r. (Unitid 65)
  - A hymn to the Virgin Mary, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 101v-104v. (Unitid 65)
    Beginning, "O Virgin, call to mind before the Keeper of Records who forgets nothing, call to mind, o Virgin, for my sake the birth through you of Him who was born in Bethlehem ...' Followed by a hymn of salutation [sälam] to the Virgin."
  - [different, larger hand], circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 105r-150v. (Unitid 65)
    a collection of hymns or songs to the Virgin Mary known as the Hymn or Canticle of the Flower [Mahlétä S'egé], beginning, "A flower appeared, shooting forth from the bone of him who greeted thee, the flower of Gabriel…".
  - blank leaf with a smaller [190 x 200mm] painted leaf sewn on, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 151r. (Unitid 65)
    containing a painting of an equestrian saint attacking a centaur. Two equestrian saints, Claudius [Gälawdéwos] and Victor [Fiqt'or] are shown in Ethiopian tradition spearing a centaur. There is no text to identify which saint is portrayed here. The painting is in the Second Gondarene style and can be dated to the 18th century.
  - blank, circa 1720; 1 item Located on folio 151v-154v. (Unitid 65)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 66: Book of Magico-Medical, Divinatory and Astrological Texts, late 19th century; Parchment manuscript in gatherings of various sizes, most frequently of 8. The thickness of the parchment varies considerably, and almost all leaves show signs of heavy wear, staining and rubbing. Single column text, varying number of lines (between 16 and 35), written in a mixture of Ge'ez and Amharic, variously in black with some rubrics, also in red, and in purple in a number of different hands. There are 32 charts and talismanic drawings (25 full-page, 7 part-page) in ink, and in addition there are 4 bifolia of coloured paintings inserted loosely into the manuscript. Bound in a plain parchment cover and preserved in a skin double carrying case with strap. (Unitid 66)
  No specific owner's name is identifiable throughout, though several prayers contain the name of a certain Gäbrä Mika'él Täsämma (sometimes just given as Gäbrä Täsämma). In addition, one of the loose bifolia contains a picture of a certain Ato Amarä Zäbehéral (? end of the second name unclear). The various hands, all of which are of poor quality, together with the paintings on the inserts, which show some western pigments, are indicative of a late 19th cent. date.
  The text comprises a typîcal däbtära's manual of various magico-medical, divinatory and astrological texts together with sample talismanic drawings. Notable is the set of charts from the divinatory text, the Awdâ Nägäst, or Cycle of the Kings.
  - Various magico-medical prescriptions, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 1r-8r. (Unitid 66)
    In Amharic.
  - Prescriptions for undoing spells, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 8v-12r. (Unitid 66)
    In Amharic with some Ge'ez.
  - Various spells for combatting demons, the evil eye, etc., late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 12r-15v. (Unitid 66)
    incorporating magical names, in Ge'ez except for one [fols. 14v-15v] which is in part at least in Arabic, or what purports to be Arabic, written in Ethiopian script.
  - Prescription for curing typhoid or typhus, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.16r. (Unitid 66)
  - Talismanic drawing in the form of an eight-pointed star with a central face, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.16v. (Unitid 66)
  - Various magical prayers for binding and destroying demons, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 17r-22r. (Unitid 66)
    Placed within the text is a further talismanic drawing in the form of an eight-pointed star and a chart. The prayers also contain "magical" or talismanic letter-forms.
  - Talismanic drawing to accompany "the prayer of Moses", late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.22v. (Unitid 66)
  - Various talismanic drawings, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 23r-24v. (Unitid 66)
  - [blank], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.25r-v. (Unitid 66)
  - Talismanic drawing in the form of the cosmic serpent, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.26r. (Unitid 66)
  - Various magical prayers for the binding and destruction of demons, evil spirits, etc., late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 27r-35r. (Unitid 66)
    Within the text are placed 4 talismanic drawings and charts.
  - [blank], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.35v. (Unitid 66)
  - Prayer for "blocking" one's enemies, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 36r-37v. (Unitid 66)
  - Sequence (in various hands) of prayers with talismanic drawings for summoning demons, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 37v-39v. (Unitid 66)
  - Prayers for "harming those who harm [me]", late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 39v-43r. (Unitid 66)
  - Prayers, some unspecified, others for female ailments, incorporating lists of magical names [asmat], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 43v-51v. (Unitid 66)
  - Astrological computations [hasabä käwakebt], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 52r-56v. (Unitid 66)
  - Computations for predicting an individual's preferment or appointment to office [hasabä simät], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.57r-v. (Unitid 66)
  - Unidentified prayer, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 57v-58v. (Unitid 66)
  - Astrological text concerning "the will of 7 stars and 12 stars' [mäfqedä 7 käwakebt wäzä-12 käwakebt], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 58v-62v. (Unitid 66)
  - Collection of unidentified magical prayers, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 63r-64v. (Unitid 66)
  - "Calculation of hours [of daylight] and of darkness" [Sefrä sä'at wäs'elalot], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 65r-68r. (Unitid 66)
    For each of the months of the year, followed by a numerical chart given the hours of daylight and darkness for the month of Tahsas.
  - [blank], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.68v. (Unitid 66)
  - 16 charts of the Awdä Nägäst [The Cycle of the Kings], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 69r-76v. (Unitid 66)
    An Ethiopian text probably originally composed in the 15th cent., which by means of circular tables [awd] allows the diviner or fortune teller to find answers to specific questions posed by his clients. The 16 tables are each named after Ethiopian lakes or rivers.
  - Prayer addressed to Jesus Christ seeking divine blessing and protection from and power over devils and spirits, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 77r-78v. (Unitid 66)
  - Unidentified divinatory text, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.79r. (Unitid 66)
  - [blank except for a single line of text], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio f.79v. (Unitid 66)
  - Astrological text, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 80r-100r. (Unitid 66)
    In Amharic, with some Ge'ez.
  - A series (30 chapters or sections) of prescriptions for casting the fortunes of men and women, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 100v-118v. (Unitid 66)
    In Ge'ez, with some Amharic.
  - "The Book of Precise Knowledge" [Mäs'hafä Temhert T'eyyuq], late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 118v-123r. (Unitid 66)
  - A series of calculations [hasab] for divining various topics, such as success of a journey, birth of children, appointment to office, etc., late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio fols. 123r-145r. (Unitid 66)
    Mostly in Ge'ez but with occasional Amharic.
  - Loose Bifolium 1, late 19th century; 1 item (Unitid 66)
    Unrelated to the text in which it is inserted.
    Front: St. George and the dragon.
    Interior: blank except for ball-pen scribbles.
    Back: Holy Trinity with the four evangelical zoa.
  - Loose Bifolium 2, late 19th century; 1 item (Unitid 66)
    Front: Virgin and Child.
    Interior left: crowned figure of Christ in the iconography of the Ecce Homo.
    Interior right: Crucifixion.
    Back: blank except for a rough drawing of a face and a pen trial.
  - Loose Bifolium 3, late 19th century; 1 item (Unitid 66)
    Front: plain cross.
    Interior left: male figure identified as Ato Amarä Behéral ( ?) with his rifle bearer; the text reads "how he put himself under the protection of Our lady Mary."
    Interior right: Ascension with the figures of Adam and Eve "risen from their sleep."
    Back: blank except for scribbles.
  - Loose Bifolium 4, late 19th century; 1 item (Unitid 66)
    The style of the drawing of the fourth bifolia differs markedly from that of the other three, and is probably by a different artist.
    Front: faint drawing of a figure.
    Interior left: St. Michael.
    Interior right: scribbles.
    Back: blank except for faint scribbles.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 72: Unidentified Text, undated; 1 item 11 x 9.2 cm (Unitid 72)
  Gift of Bruce Willsie, Class of 1986 (AM 2015-45).
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 73: Anaphora of Our Lady Mary of Cyriacus of Bhnsa, Office Prayers, circa 1800-1999; 1 item Parchment manuscript. 12 x 8 cm (Unitid 73)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 74: Missal, early 19th century; 1 item Parchment manuscript. 20.7 x 13.5 cm (Unitid 74)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 75: Asmat Prayer of the Disciples, 1900s; 1 item Parchment manuscript. 13 x 9 cm (Unitid 75)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 76: Office Prayers and Anaphora of Our Lord Jesus Christ, late 18th century; 1 item Parchment manuscript. 11.2 x 8.5 cm (Unitid 76)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 77: Homiliary in Honor of the Archangel Michael, 1800s; 1 item 20.5 x 18 cm (Unitid 77)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 78: Unidentified Text, undated; 1 item 24.5 x 18 cm (Unitid 78)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 79: Acts of Gabra Manfas, 1700s; 1 item Parchment manuscript. 18 x 16.5 cm (Unitid 79)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 80: Bible Manuscript Codex, Hymn book called Ziq, undated; 1 item Vellum manuscript. 19 x 15 cm (Unitid 80)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 81: Antiphonary for the Fast, 1800s; 1 item Parchment manuscript. 16 x 11 cm (Unitid 81)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 82: Psalter, early 18th century; 1 item Parchment manuscript. 18.2 x 15.5 cm (Unitid 82)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 83: Gadla Hawaryat Manuscript, undated; 1 item 36.6 x 29.2 cm (Unitid 83)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 84: Magical Prayers to the Virgin Mary, 1800s; 1 item 12.3 x 8.6 cm (Unitid 84)
  Gift of Bruce Willsie, Class of 1986 (AM 2015-41).
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 85: Unidentified Text, 1800s; 1 item 26 x 19 cm (Unitid 85)